Guide to the Edwin Grant Conklin Papers, 1885-1939
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Edwin Grant Conklin papers 1885-1939
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1863-1952.
6 Linear Feet 1675 Items
Edwin Grant Conklin was a biologist and an educator.
Collection contains chiefly family and professional correspondence. Includes letters addressed to Conklin; to his wife, Belle Adkinson Conklin, and to other family members. The majority of letters are written by Conklin and his wife, parents, and children. Conklin's correspondence with wife Belle pertains largely to their dating courtship. There are lettters from other relatives, friends, academic and scientific colleagues, Freedmen, educators, and Methodist clergymen.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Edwin Grant Conklin Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1992.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1863, Nov. 24 Born, Waldo, Ohio
1885 Ohio Wesleyan University, B.A.
1886 Ohio Wesleyan University, B.S.
1886-1888 Professor, Rust University (Holly Springs, Mich.)
1889 Ohio Wesleyan University, M.A.
1889-1891 Johns Hopkins University, Asst. in the biology laboratory
1890 Johns Hopkins University, Appointed biology fellow
1891 Johns Hopkins University, Ph.D.
1891-1894 Ohio Wesleyan, Chair of Biology
1892 Woods Holl, Member of the corps of instructors in charge of the Marine biological laboratory
1894-1896 Northwestern University, Chair of Zoology
1896 University of Pennsylvania, Chair of Comparative Embryology
1908-1933 Princeton University, Chair of Biology
Edwin Grant Conklin held office of President in the following service organizations: American Philosophical Society (1942-1945, 1948-1952), American Society of Zoologists (1899), American Society of Naturalists (1912), and the American Association for the Advancement of Science (1936). Conklin was awarded the John J. Carty gold medal (1942-1943), and appointed American Academy of Arts and Sciences Fellow (1914).
Collection Overview
Chiefly family and professional correspondence. Includes letters addressed to Conklin; to his wife, Belle Adkinson Conklin, and to other family members. The majority of letters are written by Conklin and his wife, parents, and children. Conklin's correspondence with wife Belle pertains largely to their dating courtship. There are lettters from other relatives, friends, academic and scientific colleagues, Freedmen, educators, and Methodist clergymen.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1863-1952
Conklin, Belle Adkinson
Education
Biologists -- Zoologists
Methodists -- United States
Freedmen -- African Americans
Courtship -- Love-letters
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1885-1939 and no date (bulk 1888-1935), (12 boxes)
  - Letters
    - Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1885-1889, Feb. (11 folders) (Box 1)
    - Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1889, Mar.-1892, Mar. (11 folders) (Box 2)
    - Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1892, Apr.-1897, Sept. (11 folders) (Box 3)
    - Conklin, Edwin Grant, ca. 1898-ca. 1906 (11 folders) (Box 4)
    - Conklin, Edwin Grant, ca. 1907-1936 (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Conklin, Belle Adkinson, 1886, June-1887, Sept. (5 folders)
    - Conklin, Belle Adkinson, 1887, Oct.-1889, Apr. 19 (8 folders) (Box 6)
    - Conklin, Belle Adkinson, 1889, Apr. 20-1897, Aug. 6 (10 folders) (Box 7)
    - Conklin, Belle Adkinson, 1897, Aug. 6-1900 (8 folders) (Box 8)
    - Conklin, Belle Adkinson, 1901-1905, May 13 (9 folders) (Box 9)
    - Conklin, Belle Adkinson, 1905, May 15-1928 (11 folders) (Box 10)
    - Conklin, Belle Adkinson, 1931-1939 (Box 11)
  - Invitations
    - Conklin, Belle Adkinson, 1885-1911, and no date (Box 11)
  - Letters
    - Adkinson, L.J. (Dr.), 1889-1903 (Box 11)
    - Adkinson, L.J. (Mrs.), 1910
    - Conklin, A.V. (Dr.), 1885-1887 (2 folders)
    - Conklin, A.V. (Mrs.), 1886-1909
    - Page, Eva Conklin, 1885-1927
    - Conklin, Paul, 1904-1907
    - Ziegler, Fanc Adkinson, 1909
  - Postcards
    - Adkinson, Albert, 1910 (Box 12)
    - Adkinson, L.J., 1885, 1910
    - Conklin, A.V. (Dr. and Mrs.), 1885-1910 and no date
    - Conklin, Belle Adkinson, 1887-1937 and no date (3 folders)
    - Conklin, E.G., 1885-1913 (2 folders)
    - Conklin, Eva, 1886
    - Conklin, Isabelle, Mary, and Paul, 1903-1922
  - Telegrams, 1886-1935 and no date
- Miscellaneous, 1885-1942 and undated, (1 box)
  Includes photographs and clippings.
  - 1888-1942, no date (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Clippings, 1886-1929 and no date